This needs to get in and if it breaks
the site, I will resign.
>> This is Michael Novati. He joined
Facebook preipo and shared a ton of
interesting early stories.
>> Like this is so much better than Zuck's
code. This is the craziest thing though.
The head of HR emailed the five of us
and was like at Facebook. He went from
an intern to a senior staff engineer in
just a few years. Was there anything
common among all the IC7 plus engineers?
>> The engineers that most impressed me. I
think you'll like the full episode since
I asked some tough questions and he was
transparent throughout. In spirit of
openness, I want to like try to talk
about it but carefully. Do you think
that LMS will kill the coding machine
archetype?
Let's get into the interview. And I
think before we go into, you know,
common topics of how you got promoted to
IC7 or staff or, you know, how you write
so much code, I wanted to go into just
you joining Meta. What was the story
behind you joining and why did you pick
Meta of all companies when it was small
at the time? I started as an intern in
May 2009 and I was in between undergrad
and grad school, which is not like the
most common internship to have. Um, I
was going to do my PhD at University of
Washington in HCI and I was like signed
up, ready to go, had my housing and
everything. I even had a research
assistantship lined up already. I really
wanted to work get some more work
experience at like a top company that
was doing really interesting kind of uh
interesting product work. Um, so I was
really only looking at at the time
Facebook and Google and I had no problem
getting interviews there, which I don't
know, nowadays it seems a lot harder to
even get those interviews, but um, it
wasn't that hard to get interviews. I
think I just applied online for both.
Um, and Meta was just like or Facebook
at the time. It was really like the
perfect team fit which is also not that
common with internships where you
actually I like happened to have
randomly interviewed with a engineer who
was working on um internal collaboration
tools which was like Meta's diff review
tools and task task tools and discussion
tools and I happened to interview with
this person and that's exactly what I
wanted to work on. I really wanted to
work on like the the social network for
work and in making people more
productive and that side of things. So I
was just like almost a perfect fit. I
did well on the lead code questions and
then uh joined his team as and he was my
manager and it started from there. So it
was really just kind of like the stars
aligning.
>> How big was the company at the time in
terms of engineers?
>> Yeah, it was about 220ish.
It's a bit there's some debate because
at the time production engineers I don't
think were like classified as software
engineers. So there was like the math
may vary a bit but it's about 200 or so.
Yeah.
>> And so, you know, I listened I did some
research and I saw that you felt like
you were one of the most into Meta's
culture engineers. What drew you so much
to Meta's culture? Like what were the
your favorite parts?
>> Yeah, it's it's really interesting. It
was both technical and also the social
vibe you I would say. So, like when I
showed up on day one, I opened up my dev
environment following the instructions
and it was like I was literally running
not the most complicated stack, but it
was even simpler at the time. I was
running Apache locally and PHP and my
dev server and it was just hitting a
database, my SQL database, just like I
would in a side project, except it was a
much larger SQL database um and a
federated one. Um, but it just felt like
a really good fit. I just like I sat
down and it just felt like I was home
kind of vibe. Um, and from that point
forward, I technically I just felt
really like in tune with with how they
were building stuff. And then socially,
I mean, honestly, Facebook was really
cool at the time. It's changed over the
years. It's had its ups and downs. Even
while I was there, I saw like the peaks
and troughs, but it was just like really
cool and it was a cool product that was
that everyone knew about and was talking
about and curious about. I could get
lots of feedback from people about like
what they liked and didn't like and it
was motivating to work on stuff that
like people cared about. Um, and I just
kind of
>> really wanted to make a good product for
all these people who cared. So, um, both
those things I think. Yeah. When I
joined Facebook and a lot of my peers
also joined as well, PHP was something
that I don't know want to say it scared.
It definitely was something that we were
not attracted to. We thought oh we had
worked with it a little bit here and
there in college was something that was
pretty unattractive. Did you feel
similarly when you joined Meta?
>> So now Meta um uses primarily hack which
is the derivative of PHP. It's kind of I
don't know if the language is officially
forked or I don't know you can you can
probably comment on that but it went
through multiple stages though to get to
hack. Um and the first step was just
having a like a compiler for PHP that
turned it into more performant code. Um
and those efforts were ongoing at the
time. And there was discussion of like
should the company change from change
rewrite the entire codebase like in Java
or Python or all these things and they
ended up just kind of optimizing the
language and starting to customize it to
address some of the deficiencies like I
think having loose typing was one of the
first things or an early thing that was
added. Yeah. So they kind of I feel like
it PHP off the shelf definitely had the
stigma at the time, but I felt like
Facebook's approach was like we're going
to make this better than any other
language could be because it's going to
be customized at a language level for
how the company uses it. So it's like
easier to use as an engineer, more
performant, and has all those traits. So
like uh both sides of that. So yes and
no is the answer.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, definitely. I think PHP
gets more of a negative rap than it
actually deserves and hack is a a much
better experience. Not it's not
comparable to PHP. So that makes sense.
Um on the culture, you know, one of the
early things that I really liked about
uh Facebook was these move fast and
break things culture. I just thought it
was such a cool framing of something
that mattered a lot to people. Since
then, that culture has changed. What are
your thoughts on on that? I was
definitely the move fast and break
things person at the time. I still like
the kind of move fast and break things
framing. Um, personally, I think that
the removing the like break things part
um it felt like it was maybe a little
bit more like the perception on the
outside. There's part of it was like
Facebook communicating to the public
didn't want to communicate that like
people are recklessly like breaking
everything. Um, but the spirit of it
wasn't it wasn't about like breaking it
wasn't like you're going around like
breaking glass all over the place and
like stepping on and cutting your feet
and like it wasn't that environment. The
idea of breaking things was breaking
norms. More recently, when you hear
people talking about first principles
thinking and like not following trends
for the sake of following them, like
breaking move fast and break things was
about like trying to break established
norms and thinking about things a
different way and trying things from
scratch and um it was a really like I
think more in the spirit of first
principles thinking than like actually
just like causing havoc. Um, so I I I
still think that that's a good good
motto if they had it today. But, um, at
the same time, like when a company's
larger, more mature, um, stability,
like even the smallest bug has millions
of dollars, tens of millions of dollars
of impact sometimes, and stability can
have a real impact. So, financial
impact. So, I think it's also I can see
also that motivation for including it
too. and your throughout your tenure. I
mean, you started when it was so small
at 200 engineers. Did you feel the
culture changing? I think you were there
earlier than I was. So, I'm curious like
how did that evolve over time? So, when
I when I joined and this was um going
back to kind of maybe what was like
appealing about Facebook at the time. Um
the culture is very engineer uh driven
at the time. It still has that today to
some extent and it's a great place for
engineers to work in one of the top
competitive places. But um it was like
to the extreme where like engineers were
very empowered to make decisions. Um
designers and product managers had to
kind of like win over the engineers and
get their buy in to build something
because if the engineer wouldn't build
it, it wouldn't get built. Um so there
was like a lot of uh like uh engineers
were empowered to push back and
negotiate with designers and engine and
I mean these are still things that
happen today but it was just another
level. The internal a lot of the almost
all the internal tools at the time were
written from scratch internally and
employees use them. So that actually
gave like it really set a tone that like
this is a company that is that is
engineering first. It builds the things
it needs. it cares a lot about like what
it's building and what it's using and
that part of the culture I like loved. I
mean the IPO in 2012 was a turning point
where the stock like crashed after the
not crashed completely but it tanked
after the IPO um because people were
like how is Facebook going to make any
money and it's like yeah that's a good
question. You know I started in 2009 and
for three years we didn't really talk
that much about like how we're going to
make money. Um, and you know, it's like
to have a to have a business that can
make money, to hire more engineers, to
build really cool stuff that hopefully
has a positive impact to you have to
like in at least capitalist society, you
have to make money to keep that going
and keep growing it. Um, so I kind of
had a more mature view as we grew and
understood how changes to optimize ads
or to changes that focused on saving
money or making more efficient
infrastructure became more important.
Um, and there was different competing
factors. I would say early on engineers
would have more like like senior
engineers would have more head-to-head
discussions about how to build stuff
like somewhat independently of
management and like towards the end you
would have more like VPs of two
different teams like negotiating stuff
and then it like percolating down. Um so
that's just an example of the
engineering empowerment um too.
>> I see. What was it like when Meta IPOed?
What was like the feeling among the
team? Was it ecstatic or people were
scared cuz the the drop in the stock
price?
>> People definitely weren't scared. Um I
would say that it was like a celebratory
moment. It started off not not being one
of those things like um I feel like Mark
Zuckerberg was really good early on
about like keeping things grounded and
humble and not getting caught up in like
headlines and the press and perception
on the outside. Um it was just very much
like you know IPOing is a very rational
thing to do to raise funding for the
company and that's what an IPO is. It's
not like a party or anything even and
and it was very rational. At the same
time though it's like it is kind of like
an event that can pull employees
together. So the actual IPO they like
got the NASDAQ to
>> there's like some button that like opens
the stock exchange or whatever. I don't
know. They got them to like bring the
button to Facebook campus and set up a
stage and like someone like rang the
bell or posted pushed the button or
whatever and like I can't there was some
talk about how they actually like hooked
that up through some special like
networking system so that it actually
was the button and not I don't it was
like some there's way more to that story
that you should dig into.
Ask ask internally about that. There's
probably something about it. But yeah,
but it was really cool. like uh Mark
Zuckerberg's parents were standing like
right beside me in the crowd and like I
even told told Mark about this story
because they just happened to be beside
me and and it was like the like kind of
tear in their eyes like it's a big
moment for like you know and you see
like kind of that person so like you see
kind of like all your friends growing up
and doing something and I thought that
part was very impactful on my life but
it wasn't like um yeah I mean
financially all the stock vested like
six months after the IPO so none of the
employees actually had like any money or
anything at the time. They were all the
same same as they were before the IPO
day. But
>> right when it vested, what was that
after it had tanked a bunch?
>> Yeah, it was actually it had tanked down
to I remember this day because me and a
bunch of it's like 20 of us. We went to
go see a movie. We were in the movie
theater and like everyone's sitting
there and then like the stock hit their
accounts. So it's like all the phones
like went off and it's like your vested
stock has been deposited. Um yeah, and
it was kind of I remember that moment.
Um but the IPO didn't really like change
people's behavior short term. I think
like much longer term like financially
people could afford houses and have kids
having kids in the Bay Area is like
super expensive. So having kids is is
even like a a thing that you a decision
you might make after having some more
savings. So like there was some impact
there longer term, but like short term
it didn't really impact people. Did you
hold because you say, "Oh, this is this
is going to go up and you know, we've
got this." Or were you the type that's
diversify, put it in index funds type
of, you know, as soon as you get
vestings?
>> I held my all my IPO stock and I still
have all of it. Um, but the
>> Oh my god, you really believe
>> But I uh sold on vest after at some
point in time, I don't remember when,
but at some point in time, I sold on
vest to diversify. It was very fortunate
for the younger people who like came out
of school and didn't have a lot of
financial literacy to have like the the
old guards so to speak who came who went
through like Google IPO and Yahoo IPO
and like there was like classes and
stuff on like how to how to man just
they were had nothing to do with like
the IPO per se just how to manage
finances and how to deal with stock like
stockbased compet I grew up in Canada
stock-based compensation was like I had
no idea what that was like I and I can
read the paperwork. I can do the math,
but like I didn't really like deeply
understand it. And it was not my day
job. And I so having these these like
lessons and stuff was was infinitely
helpful in like understanding how to
manage and how to think about the risk
and and these different things. I don't
know if they still have those classes
today, but they were very useful.
>> I mean, Meta Stock went down to like 90
or something like a year or two ago.
Were you sweating at that point or you
don't? It's just kind of out of sight,
out of mind.
>> I mean, I have like diversified enough
now that it's not like my uh retirement
like collapsed like type thing. It
wasn't that like but it was definitely
sweating a bit like
>> like oh these numbers are low like
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean cuz 90 I mean when I
started in 2018 it was like 180 or
something 150 I forgot exactly. So it
went to half of that like two years ago.
It's kind of crazy.
>> I do know people that started during
that time though who in like now three
years like almost 6x their stock which
is I mean at form so formation uh where
I'm what I'm doing now and we're helping
people prepare for interviews,
understand offers. It's definitely one
of the one of the pieces of advice I
give from just seeing these fluctuations
over the years when people are like
comparing offers and they're trying to
compare them in today's dollars headto
head and they're sweating over like
singledigit percentage differences. Like
it's a lot of money. Engineers get paid
a lot of money. It's it's reasonable to
care about like the thousands of dollars
differences, but at the same time
though, like they're kind of estimates
based off of current situation and
things change so much and stocks go up
and down and acquisitions happen and
scandals happen and like there's so many
things beyond your control that like I
always advise people to prioritize an
offer or a company that you're going to
fit really well at and perform really
well at because your performance over
time is more within your control and you
will be financially rewarded for that
performance more within your control
than trying to guess a stock um type
thing. Yeah. Yeah. No, definitely. I
mean, especially for early career, I
mean, just one promo could be, you know,
40% more compensation and relatively in
your control. So, I was talking with one
of my old managers who's been on Meta
for a long time and I mentioned that I
was going to talk to you and he said
that you had some like internal
newsletter or something that was really
popular. I'm kind of curious to learn
more about that. What What was that and
what made you start it? It sounds really
immature in retrospect, but I had this
like it was called the weekly navati.
So, I I wrote like a weekly blog post
type thing. So the notes product on
Facebook, it's like the blogging
platform type product. It was unowned
when I joined in 2009. There's no no one
product engineering wise like it was
just code that existed. So it was
something I worked on a lot at
hackathons um improving it. I added like
it was literally like plain text. It was
like you could write plain text notes
and post them. So I made I supported
rich text and one in a single hackathon.
It's uh like on 11,000. You can probably
find the PR somewhere, but uh or the
diff somewhere, but it was 11,000 lines.
I think it's like not how you build
code. So, I had to like organize a
meeting to review that code where like
get engineers in person because no one
could actually review 11,000 lines of
code. It was anyways um had rich text
editing and kind of spruce them up a
little bit. Um and it kind of evolved. I
kept adding a couple things here and
there, tags. Uh, I was kind of using it
a little bit like dog fooding, which is
a big thing at at Facebook, like using
the product yourself and poking holes in
it and trying to give feedback and stuff
like that. So, yeah, I was using it
myself to post a lot of notes in general
and then um I had a couple of posts that
were just slightly controversial
controversial about like product
building and yeah, different like kind
of hot topics and they got a lot of
traction and discussion. So, I started
posting more regularly. Some of them
were very off-the-cuff, like random
things. Like there's one that was like,
"If I was CEO, what would I do?" Um,
Facebook was adamant about only having a
Menllo Park campus and not having
anything in San Francisco. And I was
like, "We need to have stuff in San
Francisco. All the new startups like
Stripe and Uber, they're all in San
Francisco and they're like taking our
employees and everyone wants to be there
and all the employees are moving to San
Francisco." And like Facebook was just
like, "No San Francisco office. No San
Francisco office." So, I was posting a
lot about that and I had like one post
about how they should open a South San
Francisco office and that actually
happened. So, I was happy that that one
like came true.
>> When you look back on that writing, um
because I know some people do advocate
like, you know, you should start some
sort of internal, you know, post in some
Slack group or workplace group or email
newsletter just internally. Would you
recommend it? Like were there outcomes
from that that looking back you say that
was a great idea?
>> Overall I would say that was not a good
idea in retrospect.
>> Oh really? Um why is that?
>> So okay there wasn't a strategic reason
to do it. It was really like I call it
like open and transparent and I think it
comes from Facebook values. Facebook's
values of being open. Um at the time
that was like a a strong value. Um, and
I really just believe in like removing
like removing like the kind of surface
pleasantries and facades and like what
are things like more objectively and
like what can we do? How can we improve
them or like if you build a product and
it got like a lot of traction but it was
there's always some luck involved. But
if it was more like the circumstances
that made the product grow and not the
substance, we want to be like real about
that. Like this is awesome. we got
really lucky that this product took off
and it's not that great. We need to
improve it. Um whereas like I see a lot
of startups, a lot of boot camps like if
they get a lot of little bit of traction
um they kind of like think that that's
how that it must be justification that
the thing they built was awesome and
they kind of like don't hold the like
highest bar to keep ruthlessly iterating
on it. a bit of a tangent, but my
generally my like philosophy is to be
just fairly like open and direct and I
want people to be that way with me and
like create that environment where
people are just okay talking about
stuff. So, it was really about pushing
Facebook's values and trying to have a
company where people feel open about
talking about things and it had nothing
to do with like performance reviews or
growing influence or anything like that.
It was like there was no other
motivation. But in retrospect, I would
say I would not do it because actually
caused this is like something I didn't
deal with well at the time and I still
don't know how I would have dealt with
it if it caused some like friction and
tension sometimes like there was one
post where I just openly called out that
uh Facebook has software engineer job
titles where you can like be a software
engineer and move around to different
teams and it's a pretty like it's what
you think of canonically as like the
software engineer but then they had all
these other engineers like network
engineer data engineer and those
engineers like couldn't change teams
easily. They were hired to like teams
and they weren't quite like the same
like privileges as a software engineer.
And I just like called this out very
openly like out of the blue. And I
didn't realize that that was like a big
tension behind the scenes and it like
caused a lot of like friction with
different executives who were like
Michael I'm working on this problem. I
didn't like really did not help us to
like call this out like we have to do
damage control now like we need to talk
about this and it like kind of that
off-the-cuff style like does have
consequences. So I learned that
>> and I try to try to adopt that still
today but I still am very big on on
Reddit and on LinkedIn on just trying to
be like direct and open and unfiltered a
little bit with with thoughts
>> to try to show people that it's okay to
do that. Did HR ever reach out to you
saying hey you got to take that down?
>> Uh
yes. There were not issues with sketchy
type things like oh this is like uh you
need to take this down like for the comp
like I don't know. Um, but I got
feedback from HR on certain things. Like
I had a post that was about which
companies are like hiring Facebook like
poaching Facebook engineers and Uber was
like giving Facebook engineers like very
large stock grants at the time and HR
was like not super they gave me feedback
that like that kind of post they thought
it could incentivize people to like
explore other opportunities. Um, and
they, it's not like I can't do it, but
they just, it was just more like
feedback that like, hey, did you realize
that you might incentivize people to
like consider other opportunities
unintentionally with that post? And I
was like, no, I didn't realize that. And
it's like these were more off-the cuff
thoughts and maybe it wasn't worth the
the friction. But
>> yeah. Yeah. Even in that case, I like
when I got that feedback about the
engineers going to competitors, I was
like a bit concerned and I messaged Mark
Zuckerberg directly and asked him like
how he felt about it and he was totally
fine with it and encouraged me to keep
posting. So I like felt like it was like
okay to do that and I I was still
motivated to keep keep posting. But
yeah,
>> you could directly message Mark
Zuckerberg and he would reply. Yeah, I
mean when I joined Facebook was quite
small. So I like interacted with Bos I
think was my direct manager, skit
manager for a while and I regularly
interacted with him even when I left
like I messaged all the executives
one-on-one like Chris Cox and Shrep and
Jay and Bos and and Zach and like told
them I'm leaving and you know they
responded thanking me for the
contributions and stuff like I feel I
had a relationship with all the people
all the executives at the time but it
was kind of from joining when it was
small and from just genuinely
interacting with them I'd say of all The
people though Mark I like got to know
more personally too outside of work a
little bit and have like the closest
relationship with him of all the
executives but I have not talked to many
of them for the past couple years as
Facebook has really like exploded but
yeah
>> when you had just joined I guess 200
people probably not but did Zuck still
write any code like did you ever see a
diff from him
>> I actually worked with him on a
hackathon in 2009 Zach had this
hackathon idea where he was like I think
that anyone should be able to put like
any emoji to any post as a reaction. And
this was like in 2009 and now this is
actually like the norm everywhere. So he
was right.
>> I was like a bit skeptical but I thought
like it sounded like technically
feasible that I could help build that.
So I I was like working with him on that
during a hackathon and uh with another
engineer Tom Whitner. We kind of got it
working but uh the code was just so bad
we it never got shipped at the time. But
he Mop just like did not give up on that
idea though. And like I remember when um
I think Sammy Krug I think is still at
Meta. But I think she was the PM if I
remember correctly. She was the PM who
like led the reactions initiative and
when it launched I was like wow like
this it was done like properly and well
and like well designed and well
implemented like this is so much better
than Z code.
But uh there's also another there was
another time though where he actually
merged a PR and this is actually like a
Facebook like this is a crazy story but
um there was like this lockdown period
in 2010 where Facebook was very
concerned about plus um potentially
making a dent into Facebook's user base
and there was a lockdown period where
they really wanted to ship like a bunch
of features really fast. There was food
served on the weekend. It was like
pretty pretty intense and I was like
again the all in person so I was there
like all weekend but during that period
I at one of the company uh Friday Q&A
companywide Q&As's I basically made a
bet with Zuck that he wouldn't like if
he was able to commit code by the end of
lockdown then I would like stop
ripsticking which was a skateboard like
thing that was very dangerous that's now
banned
>> that I would do around the office and
then if he didn't commit the code I I
can't remember what the penalty was and
I don't remember what it was.
>> Ripstick is that thing that like you go
like this, right?
>> Yeah. You have to two wheeled skateboard
and you have to like wiggle your hips. I
like got got really good at it. But um
it was really dangerous. So like a lot
of there's rumors that Facebook's health
insurance premiums were significantly
higher than other tech companies because
these ripsticks were like scattered
throughout the office and there were so
many injuries. Ripsticks were eventually
banned I think in like 2012ish.
This is the craziest thing though. The
week before the formal ban went into
place, the head of HR emailed like the
five most prominent rip stickers at the
company, the head of HR emailed the five
of us and was like, "Can you give us
feedback on this draft banning ripsticks
and at draft email banning ripsticks?"
And at the I didn't realize this, but
this is like a classic technique to try
to get buy in from like opponents is to
like
>> try to bring them into the process more.
So this was actually like a a buy like
hey like hey you know ripsticks are
going to get banned but can you give us
like feedback on how we communicate this
like I want to talk to her about like
this part of her job but I just can't
imagine being like the head of Facebook
HR like tens of thousands of people and
like having to ban ripsticks and having
to get buy in from like these critical
Um or else it could be like a revolt.
That was like a big tangent. But yeah, I
I just
>> Oh yeah. What about the Zuck thing or he
merged the PR and Okay.
>> basically it was a Yeah. bat in front of
the whole company and then he actually
like merged the PR.
>> Um so then I think I was banned from
riding ripsticks
out indoors or outdoors. I think they
like qualified it just to there was like
a loophole. But yeah, there's these all
these stories of like early Facebook
where Zach actually wrote a lot of the
code. When you first got there, was a
lot of it, you know, you look at the git
blame or I don't know what what uh
source control early was. Would you see
like those people's names in there?
>> Yeah. Um occasionally, yeah, there was a
bit I think there was a wave of
engineers like in the Facebook kind of
internal lore. the first engineers at
Facebook were not known to be writing
the like best quality code per se. Um,
but they wrote code fast and like they
did a good job of what they were doing.
But there there's kind of like this like
wave of engineers where mic um where
Facebook got like poached a bunch of
former Harvard people from Microsoft. I
think Bos was in that wave too. Um but
there was kind of like a wave of more
like mature or slightly more experienced
engineers who came in started laying out
more more structure and framework and
then they also brought in some other
people at the time who really started
writing like more of the core
abstractions and the stuff that was the
foundation for the product
infrastructure team. Um I don't know if
the team still exists today but um it
existed for a really really long time.
um who builds all those core
abstractions and maintains them and
um that wave of people their names are
like all over the code base like Evan
Priestley and Putnham and um these
people. So these were my role models
when I joined when I wanted to be the
coding machine who writes a lot of code
and I saw these people's names. I was
like those were kind of my role models
of who I wanted to be.
>> Yeah. I'm kind of curious, you know, you
you grew into such a strong engineer,
uh, senior staff, IC7. Who were the
other engineers that you looked at that
you said those people really impressed
me and why? The engineers that most
impressed me was the product
infrastructure team working on like the
React framework uh nowadays, but at the
time it was more like the PHP
abstractions. Um like Nick Shrock and
Ola and um the they were kind of it was
like building out the the end framework
of today like that was built through my
time. So I saw that kind of get
constructed brick by brick and those
people I kind of saw as like the best
engineer kind of thing. Uh Dan Schaefer
I think Dan Schaefer might still be I'm
not sure but I saw those engineers as
people as a different type of engineer.
They were that was not like the thing
that was not my specialty. So the person
who was most like me was this person
Evan Priestley who I think was like the
number one committer before me. I don't
know if he invented clown I don't know
if you still have clown town. This idea
of clown town was like if you like
caused a really bad silly bug or typo or
something or like you break Maine or
something like that, you would be like
added to Clown Town philosophically.
>> Oh,
>> he had a a certain type of humor, I
would say. But but he he was very
prolific. He single-handedly wrote uh
the diff diffol camp at the time which
became fabricator and like when he left
they forked they kind of open sourced it
and like wrote all of that entire
product suite from scratch like himself
basically if let's say you are you know
you're building your own team and you
could either have him on your team to
build out this new product or you can
have four senior engineers just regular
other senior engineers, you know, which
would you rather take?
>> Uh, Evan Priestley.
>> Wow. Okay. So, how how many senior
engineers does it take to you would pick
them over Evan? So, it depends on the
context of what you're building. And
like this is something too that comes up
with like came up with me a lot too is
like if you have like this branding as
like this person who just like writes a
lot of code. It's like they're not like
it's not like a mysterious process where
like the code just magically appears or
something like like it comes from just
work hard work and it comes from keeping
like a bunch of code in my like RAM in
my head like my memory like and and
paying attention to like the littlest
details and really getting absorbed in
it. And like if you put me on like a
brand new product, like if if you were
like Michael's a coding machine, let's
put him on like Oculus
uh firmware or something, I like would
not be productive at first. It would
probably take me a really long time to
absorb everything and suck everything
in, but it's not like just have like
this magic power to do that. So I think
it depends a lot on the context. Like uh
if you're at a company and everyone's
already ramped up on the thing and you
have that choice, I would probably
choose the the coding machine. Um, if
you're doing something like really like
new, you might actually want like a
little bit more diverse backgrounds and
diverse experiences so that there's a
little bit more like flexibility and
creativity in the process. Um, so I
would actually qualify that as context
dependent. But all things equal in a
comfortable codebase, I would want the
coding machine. I have like many many
examples over the years of things that
like just like would not have happened
if it wasn't for the single person
whether it's me or Evan Priestley or a
similar coding machine like there it's
like that's kind of what makes you the
coding machine at that level is you're
like doing something that people did not
think was possible and you're making it
actually happen. Can you give an example
where you know something where you or
Evan succeeded where you know a team of
seven senior engineers would not have
brought that through the finish line.
The like canonical example for myself is
um there's this framework called
preparables.
Um it was a framework that in a given
component separated the rendering code
from the data fetching code. Um so like
a given component on the screen um would
have a data fetching function and a
rendering function so that you could
kind of in different p waves fetch all
of the data in parallel
wait for it all to be fetched and then
render everything. Those concepts have
matured a lot now in React and all of
the like complexities with with suspense
and spending and all these like more
intricate things. At the time it's
fairly simple just like component two
functions fetch data render at that
framework basically got replaced over
time with async await and uh more modern
things. But there was thousands of
classes throughout the codebase that
people would be interacting with on a
daily basis that were preparable
structured. Um, and I like
manually relentlessly remove refactored
and removed every single preparable
until literally the the parent class was
removed from the codebase. Um, and I
think there was three like three, five,
six thousand of them or something. Um,
it did take several months, but like I
don't think that would have happened
>> and it was single-handed effort. Um, and
I don't think that would have happened
otherwise,
>> believe it or not. Now there's like a,
you know, there's like a routing
framework to route all of the like URL
URL requests like to the right like
endpoints. It's like abstracted now. I
mean, it's been abstracted for many
years now, but when I joined, there was
still like PHP endpoints that were hit
directly on the server like kind of old
school web development. Um, and another
project I did was to remove every single
one of those and only use like the
routing framework.
>> Um, and it's again like something that
>> if there wasn't like the drive, the
grit, the priority, it wasn't like,
you know, it wasn't like the most
important thing for the company, but
like those things wouldn't have
happened. They would have taken a lot
more resources that could be working on
like new products to do. and one person
just single-handedly doing it can make
all the engineers lives a little easier
to not have to deal with these legacy
frameworks and stuff.
>> I mean what you just described a large
scale refactoring or super coding heavy
task I could see an LLM doing that job
quite well um in the future or maybe
even now to be honest and so my question
is do you think that LM will kill the
coding machine archetype? So when I was
doing all this work at at Facebook, I
was using Vim. And the tools I used were
like this thing called TBGS,
which I don't know if it still exists,
but it was just an indexed search of the
entire codebase, but it was a
proprietary tool outside of any IDE,
like a command line tool or a web tool.
Um, so I used that to find things. And I
think I had tab completion in Vim, like
a plugin
for like class names. That was it. Um
and I was very productive. So even if I
would have had like VS code with modern
tools that we have now, I probably would
have been more productive. So the the
current wave of AI tools and the LLM
based AI tools um are kind of like a
next step of going from Vim to VS Code.
It's like going to a LLM AI powered mode
that lets you be more productive, makes
certain things faster, certain
refactorings faster and changes faster.
The next evolution going into like that,
you know, we're seeing some some agentic
flows in coding popping up already. Um,
some success cases here and there. Um,
it's not like mainstream. I think that
those flows will probably be
even more replacing of like those basic
functions right now though like and
probably for it's changing so fast. It's
never things have never changed this
fast. But like for this year, I think
that AI and LLM tools like a lot most
people most engineers still don't use
them. Like you get off YouTube and
Reddit and all these places like and you
just go to the middle and no middle of
somewhere and ask an engineer like
they're not using AI tools as much as
like the the people who are pushing the
leading edge. Um so if like everyone
used the tools the way the like leading
productive people are using them then we
would have a massive industry change
already and we would all be more
productive including the coding
machines. Um, and then the agentic flows
that happen after that, like I don't I
don't know. I not uh I'm not decided yet
on how that's going to impact the coding
machine and or the rest of engineers as
well because that's going to really
change things probably even more than
we've ever seen before.
>> What's the biggest difference between
you know how you used to work? I mean
you mentioned this Vim workflow is
basically your hand writing the code and
doing everything yourself to using the
LMS. like what are the biggest
differences you noticed?
>> I'm in a code base that's 500,000 lines
give or take, which is not a small
codebase, not a tiny codebase, but it's
like the size of a popular like
open-source big project. It's a
reasonably sized codebase, but it's
small enough that I like still know most
of the code structure in my head and the
and and everything. So I'm not using
that many uh codewide agentic flows um
or multifile flows in general sometimes
but not often. Um I'm normally using AI
to speed up what I would already do. So
I already almost know the code I would
want to write and I'm using LLMs to
generate that code faster. Um, if I want
to write an entire component that I
think is going to be like a 100 lines of
of markup for the page,
um, if I I have to make a real-time
judgment call, if I can type those lines
faster or if I can explain in the most
efficient prompt possible to an LLM in
the right spot how to generate those
lines for me and have it be successful.
Um, and I'm
just, you know, prompt by prompt
building up that intuition on how to
effectively give those prompts to speed
up my workflow. Um, and I'm in a spot
right now where I'm like very much more
productive. Like we have a product, we
are adding new features. Like the
workflows are kind of pretty similar now
that they have been six months ago for
our product development process. And I'm
producing like five times more code than
I was then just through these
optimizations. And it's changing so
fast. So it's not like there's an
endgame here. Um it's not like there's
this fixed path. It's like every every
time a new model comes out I'm
developing different intuitions or a new
feature or a new Yeah. Um a new command
line tool stuff like that. Yeah. So it's
interesting time for sure to be an
engineer in general.
>> It's interesting. I mean today and maybe
soon also it just uh it seems like LLMs
are an extension another thing to
delegate to that makes us more
productive. You mentioned the agentic
stuff if it can kind of uh more
independently generate code without the
software engineer being involved. I
wonder how would you feel if coding was
more of a hobby in the future and
programming was no longer driven by
humans? Uh, I think it's a cool future.
We talk about all the cool things that
engineers do and and why it's so awesome
to be a software engineer, but like if
you actually clock your time and look at
what you do as an engineer, there's a
lot of stuff that's like copy paste,
search, copy, paste, change some lines,
like sit there and stare at the screen
and think for a bit. Like there's a lot
of things that are like not as fun. And
if you could really just like focus on
the fun parts like the creative product
pieces or even sometimes just like
building
I find joy and excitement in like
cleaning up code and combining things
that didn't seem like they have any
overlap and merging them into one like
frame one concept like like there's
things like that that I just like doing
that maybe as a hobby or maybe it's just
like Sergey Brin at Google's probably
like the perfect example of this where
he can just like plop into whatever he
wants to work on um and like contribute
what he wants to contribute there and
like it's more he's doing what he wants
to do and there's and not the day-to-day
stuff. So I think it's probably it's
exciting in some sense in that sense for
sure.
>> Um it's definitely like scary to the
software engineering profession because
it kind of like raises like what does it
mean to be a software engineer? Is it
actually writing the code? Is it
architecting the data models? Is it
coming up with the systems level stuff?
Is it gluing it all together? Like it
and it's kind of a AI is already just
making us think about those things. And
I think it's going to be redefined many
times over in the next few years. Like I
think we're in this really weird
transition phase though where for the
next little while, I don't know how
long, but next little while like AI and
LLM tools are going to make engineers
more productive. specifically engineers
with a lot of experience and strong
taste are going to be more and more
productive. And if you're not an
engineer with lots of experience, it's
going to be harder and harder to to
build that. Um, which is I'm more
confident in that. But in the future
beyond that, like if AI can write its
own code and maintain its own code, I
don't think code will be the same as it
is today. Like it's if an AI can do its
own thing, it's not going to be writing
JavaScript. it's going to be managing
its own services that have like a an API
and it it's gonna do its thing. Like you
might not know how it's building it and
as long as that API is contractually
provided and it is doing its thing and
meeting whatever specifications it has
to then it doesn't really matter how
it's being built and it might be like
doing its own thing and no one might
know what that code looks like and it
might not even be readable. I mean
engineers make a lot of mistake like
it's like humans make a lot of mistakes
with code and cause really bad bugs and
AI is probably going to have bugs and
it's going to have ways to fix them and
it's not like it's going to like we are
going to build AI to to do those things.
It's going to be like I don't think it's
going to be like this dystopian future
overnight. It's going to be step by step
as we get there. And I think it's not
going to feel and I think it's going to
happen. So I don't think we should push
back on it. we should be thinking about
like how do we make this AI world the
best that it can be instead of like
pushing back that it can possibly work.
That's where I stand on that. But yeah,
>> you you mentioned there were some React
engineers that you looked up to and
their archetype was different from
yours. What what impressed you about
what they were doing? What how would you
describe the archetype? Yeah, I don't I
it might fall under the specialist
archetype where you're really really
really good at one stack. Um, another
example is like this engineer who knew
email protocols and was like one of the
10 people in the world who deeply
understood email protocols
to like I know that like you can look up
the specs but like the practical side
too of like dealing with spam and
routing and all this stuff and like you
know so there's like I think it falls in
a specialization um bucket um like in
general I'm like the fan of the sports
team analogy so like you want like a
professional sports team that where
every every every player on a baseball
team can play like any position like
pretty well. Even like the pitchers who
only throw can probably hit the ball
better than most typical people or like
even amateur baseball players. Like so
it's kind of like you want your team to
have those different roles and you want
to respect each other's place on the
field. Um, so I kind of respect those
those engineers for what what they do
and I have like my thing and I think
that the whole team is exceptional if it
has these different these different
players.
>> I see. So what impressed you about those
engineers is that they solve problems
that other people couldn't.
>> Yeah. And uh the abstractions they were
creating specifically were very
impactful because all the engineers are
using them on a daily basis. So like a
lot of the coding machine work I'm doing
that impacted everyone was like cleaning
up and making their lives easier. Um and
these engineers were writing frameworks
that were like that made the like
thought process less overhead for an
engineer to fetch data and stuff like
that. Um so there were some similarities
a little bit but that I like respected
that work a lot. Um, but it's very hard
to come up with such an elegant API
that's super performant and is easier to
use. Making things simpler is sometimes
more work than writing a lot of code or
harder work, too. So, I respected them
for that. I wanted to talk a bit about
your career growth cuz you grew to, you
know, senior staff or IC7 at Facebook.
Um, there were less IC7s at that time,
so it's even more impressive that you
did that and as quickly as you did it.
Um, so I'm I'm curious to kind of dig
into some of the, you know, behind the
scenes in it. I I think you've told the
story publicly a few times, so I kind of
want to ask some of the the side topics
on it. So, um, one thing I'm curious
about, you mentioned somewhere that you
had spent 30% of your time on your
team's work and about 70% of your time
on side projects or projects of your own
initiative. How how does that work if
you know you're getting work from your
current team? Can you talk about that? I
think the way I framed it is like almost
being like a senior engineer on a small
team of 10 people and then um spending
like more than half my time doing kind
of codebase wide initiatives, cleanup,
refactorings, a new framework, sometimes
some random
random oneoff thing a team needs help
with or something like that. Um
emergency like other work. Um, so like
the I would say like the 30% work very
much like if you just imagine having an
E5 on your team like it's not like time.
It wasn't like I'm it wasn't like 30% of
my 8 hour day was the team and it's like
only contact me then. It was more like
30% of my mental space or my focus I
think. So I would still be like on the
team all day long. I would be um as like
a senior person you're reviewing a lot
of code. You're bouncing ideas off more
junior people. You're mentoring, helping
junior people grow in scope to get
promoted from entry level to midlevel.
Those kinds of things. Um writing a lot
of code on features that the team queued
up like the team had um just you know um
contributing to them. um going to like
product meetings and contributing to
like the product direction evaluating
feasibility of things like when product
managers like we want to do ABC and it's
like okay well A and B I think we the
team can do C they can't do like you
know general things a senior engineer
would do but the volume of code produced
was more like a senior engineer on the
team I would say how did you manage the
relationship with your team or you know
your manager for instance
typical manager knows you have bandwidth
kind of positions you in a certain area
but it's a little unconventional if that
that IC is doing majority of their
bandwidth is solving problems all over
the place so how did you manage that
relationship I would often report not
all the time but I often reported to
more junior managers and I was almost
like a peer like the skip would
generally do my performance reviews but
I would like report to a or junior
manager, I would almost like help them
manage the team and then like really
report to the skip kind of thing. Um
like unofficially report to them like
vibe. So it was definitely like
interesting relationships like the head
of like one of the VPs I would meet with
like monthly for the whole org and my
skip level I would meet with like every
two weeks. So in the org chart, you
reported to a a frontline manager, but
in practice, you were almost dotted line
reporting to some more senior people and
you were known as a it's almost like a
weapon of the org that you kind of just
go wherever.
>> You know, let's say I'm a I'm a senior
engineer and I want to go solve problems
for the org all over the place and I'm
reporting to my frontline manager. I got
my tickets or whatever. How how did you
transition into that IC7 solving the
hardest problems for the org role?
>> Is in my case like I was almost like the
coding machine from day one and the
thing that improved was my taste and
judgment but the like even the raw
output was probably honestly the same
when I was like a week into Facebook. Um
like there was there was two different a
fork of the task tool. Um it was called
Laltana and Cortana and it was the same
like data source for the internal task
management tool and there was two
different like UIs. One was like
streamlined and fast and one was like
bloated with features and slow and there
was like competition between them. And
like I in like a week or less I merged
the two code bases into one that was
like the speed of the like slim down one
with all the features of the bloated
one. Um and it was I just like literally
just took the initiative entirely on my
own. I didn't even like tell anyone. I
mean, this is so early on. You could not
do this now, but like I didn't tell
anyone. I just mer merged them. I posted
to the entire company. I'm like, "The
tools are merged. Like, it's done. Like,
deal with it kind of vi vibe." Not not
in a mean way, just like it's done like
like surprise. Um,
>> right
>> that So, what what I learned along like
the output was really the same. What I
learned though was like that's not the
best way to like merge tools that are
used by hundreds of people to just be
like surprise like URLs changed like
deal with it. like I didn't deeply
understand like the consequences for
teams. Everyone like like patted me on
the back and thought it was amazing
because like no one could have done
this. So like all overall it was still
positive but like that would not be like
like the the things I learned were like
judgment calls about like the scope to
change things at um the the how to like
pay attention to the impact the changes
will have on other people. Building up
intuition about what spots are more
sensitive than others to make changes
in. Um, and that like judgment of doing
these massive things like over and over
and over again and doing some of them
too fast and having too many bugs and
there's some people who will like
forever not like me because I like
caused a really bad bug because I went a
little like made a bad judgment call and
then I learn take the feedback and then
keep going at the same speed while like
improving my judgment and building that
taste. Um, and I think that accumulation
of judgment and taste is what crosses
the line into the E7, but the raw
output, it wasn't like the raw output
kept going up. Um, so I don't
necessarily have advice on how to build
that because I think you have to kind of
like it's very dependent on your or your
team, but I think like if you want to do
that, I would start by talking to your
manager and if they can't really help,
maybe talk to your skip level manager
and if that doesn't really help, try to
find a really senior engineer who is
maybe that person and ask them how they
did it in that same org as you or in
their org similar to yours like it's
kind of um it's very dependent on the
context but yeah
>> if I'm understanding correctly then you
were able to work on all this
extracurricular you know orgwide
projects because you had such high
productivity and that was true from day
one and you had the initiative too like
no one no one's going to stop you like
let's say you you have your your project
on your team no one's going to stop you
from doing extra work that solves some,
you know, problem on the side. And so
you you took that initiative and you
have exceptional productivity. So you
just became known as this person that's
constantly solving like extra problems.
Um yes, but I I really think that the
jud the judgment and taste piece though
is like so critical. Um and it's more
than just the code. It impacts like the
push process. So like now there's
continuous integration at Facebook. At
the time there wasn't. If you broke
something and it shipped to production
and you needed a fix like the pushing
team like would not generally be happy
and you have to like negotiate with them
in a sense and if you break things too
much they don't trust you and they will
not accept your changes. They might even
push back on your normal changes. So
that hurts a coding machine. So, I have
to like build a relationship with the
pushing team so they really trust me.
And more than once I've said like this
needs to get in and if it breaks the
site I will resign like quote unquote.
I've said that
>> because I burned credibility before like
the day before shipping something too
fast. I had to be very sure, so sure
with the fix that I would like you can
fire me if it breaks things and like
those types of like things to build that
that trust and credibility like another
engineer who just shows up and writes a
lot of code probably would not be able
to get away with it because they didn't
have the years of building that up. So
it's a that that is really important.
It's not only the raw it's like much
more than the raw output there.
>> Would you have resigned if you if you
broke broke it again and you said you
would? Yeah, I think I would have.
>> It's like this weird maybe it's a
personality trait, but it's like it puts
that saying that puts so much pressure
on me that I will like make sure that it
does not break. You know, like
>> I will like I will like triple check
every line. I will think about every
weird case that could possibly happen.
Yeah.
>> You talked about taste and judgment when
it comes to code and software
engineering. What does that mean? Like
people who cook with like cast iron
pans, they talk about building a patina
where you have to like build up layers
of like history and it gets burned into
the pan and it has a a profile. Um
that's to me is like taste. There are
some people who who naturally have
instincts for maybe it comes from this
the way they grew up and their past
experiences they have and the the
context they're in. and they're they
have stronger taste faster, but
generally it just requires like
experience in some way. Like you might
have experience outside of code that
might build up you might do lots of like
dancing and you build up all this like
intuition and muscle memory about
dancing or sport. Other sports and stuff
too are similar. Um, it's kind of like
that but in the coding context of you
might read a book on how to be the best
like uh the fastest speed skater. You
read the book and you just got to put
the skates on and you just have all the
ambition and you just want to be the
fastest. You know you can do it. It's
like you're you you have to like spend
years doing it and really like feel it
like building up every aspect of the
muscle memory, every like movement on
the ice, the feel of the ice under
different temperatures and altitudes and
pressures and like the sharpness of
different skates. You'll be able to feel
the difference between like a skate that
was used once versus twice. Like it's
like every detail you will over time
accumulate by putting in the time and
gaining that experience. Um, and I see
far too many people rushing early on
where in their careers where they're
trying to like jump ahead. They're
they're trying to enter the Olympics as
a speed skater and they have not like
they haven't built that yet. And that's
okay. Like you can't build it overnight.
And there's nothing wrong with you. And
I advise people to like put in the the
practice and the reps. And I mean at
formation it's really important to get
feedback because if you just do this
without feedback then you don't improve.
If you kind of set yourself up to do
practice, get feedback, iterate, and
really have the grit to keep go
following through on that, then you can
get to that super top tier stage of I
think like any any skill.
>> So when you say taste, are you saying uh
like your intuition behind how you
design software or are you talking about
problem taste like which problems are
worth solving for the business? Which
code matters more? both for different
people like a product and a product
manager is their taste is probably more
in terms of prioritizing what products
features to build and they probably buil
they build that up through building lots
of products failing failing building
something doesn't work building
something doesn't work all the junior
product managers super ambitious they
just need to keep shipping things and
seeing what doesn't work and they build
that up um and then you see the like
exceptional product managers like 90% of
the stuff they shipped was like not good
at or failed for some
Um, and that's why they're so good is
because they learned all they learned
each step of the way and then they made
changes and grew from it. So I'm talking
about that for an engineer that applies
to like or for me at least that applies
to code itself and writing code and the
strategies to moving really fast and
stuff like that. Yeah. you mentioned
about uh changing other people's code or
the social norms around touching code
that other people own and you know you
said something about landing a bug in
that codebase kind of really could blow
up in your face. So did you ever get
feedback from other teams because it
sounds like you were kind of touching
everyone's code and how did you handle
that feedback? Like I think there were
some times where like you know going
into a codebase replacing some old like
framework that on like the live version
of their tool the team's tool um and
they were already building a newer tool
and maintaining like carefully
maintaining backwards compatibility and
they have lots of like diffs and pull
requests in play that were like they had
like their thing going and by like just
showing up refactoring at some some
stuff in the old tool and then leaving
it like made their it caused a lot of
merge conflicts for all their stuff in
progress and they like weren't happy
about it. um and they wanted to like
revert the change from the code because
they didn't want to have to deal with
like merging that into their complex uh
change, right? Um and that's feedback to
be careful for that stuff like I would I
would didn't pay attention to that. So
it's like okay that is one one use case
where you got to be careful is if teams
are working on complex longer term thing
migrations already like be careful in
that area of the code.
>> What about the case of ownership? So,
you know, software isn't just about
creating it, but there's all this
management and maintenance burden after
it's created. Did any team get upset? I
said, "Hey, you add this feature, great,
but who's owning this thing now? Who's
going to actually maintain it?" That
didn't come up for me. And I don't know
if it's the philosophy. I don't know if
it's still the case, but the philosophy
back then was like every line of code
you wrote, you're responsible for. Um
Kent Beck talked about this recently
that yeah he was like it's a really
strong sense of ownership. So like if
you if you are okay being woken up at
3:00 a.m. and you're going to respond
and fix some bug in your code any time
of the day anywhere then like do what
you want with like you know don't write
tests then go ahead as long as you're
maintaining it. If you don't want that
and you want to work nine to five, then
you might want to write more tests to
make sure that your code's stable when
you're not around. Um, so I think if I
like I I didn't just like touch code,
didn't refactor code and forget it. I
was responsible if there was any bugs
and then in the future like sometimes
two years later there's like something
that I get an automatic bug assigned to
me because it's like you touched this
code last and I'm like oh man, I don't
even remember doing this. Um, but then I
would fix the bug because even though I
didn't cause the bug, it was just like
that is now my code. Um, now I didn't I
didn't have any territorial conflicts
because I don't I don't know why I I
didn't I just didn't really come up. Um,
I never I didn't like step on people's
product
judgment. I mean, this is part of the
the judgment calls I guess that you're
building up. Like it it's kind of like
performing a surgery and you're not
really like you got to be really careful
about what you're changing. You don't
want to impact.
Like I said, I learned maybe learned the
hard way from making some mistakes early
on and being a bit too aggressive in
certain areas. Like you start to learn
where that line is between
um like messing up people's day-to-day
and
not and still getting the refactoring or
the cleanup done. One thing that I'm
curious about you, as you become a more
senior engineer, it's very common to get
pulled into more and more meetings.
miscellaneous overhead. How did you
manage your your focus as you got
promoted to be a coding machine? You
must have had a lot of focus time even
as IC7.
>> I really try to minimize my meetings. If
someone like just added I don't know if
this still happens, but people would
like just make meetings, add you to the
calendar, there's no context. It's just
like something something like sync.
You're like, I don't know what this is.
I like would ask like what is this? Um,
which I think people maybe I don't know
if it's still like the the norms have
changed, but I would push back on a lot
of meetings. Um, I generally didn't do
like go to standups unless it was like
relevant. Like there's a we're working
really hard to ship to something in a
month. I need to go to the standup every
day because it's like important to be on
pace. But if there was like a standup
that was more like just social chitchat
like cuz the team I don't know some
standups end up being that way. I don't
know if you've seen them, but like it
happens and I would not generally go to
those. Um, but yeah, so just being
pretty pretty strict about time and then
also like having the manager support was
like pretty important. like I wouldn't I
was pretty choosy and I like went on
very I made very conscious team changes
when I whenever I did change teams and
the manager was like very like in tune
with like managers at Meta um like their
job is to make their reports perform
exceptionally well. I think I don't know
if that's how you would summarize it in
one sentence, but like um like if your
if your reports get promoted and have a
lot of impact, like that's what makes
you a recognized as a high performing
manager too. And so my managers are
generally trying to pro like protect me
and manage me so that I can have the
most impact possible, which means not
getting pulled into a lot of meetings
where unnecessary. But I also I think I
was too arrogant sometimes and that's
like one of the things I would tell my
older self. Um like sometimes I I I
definitely remember walking out on a
meeting or two where I was just like I
don't think this meeting is useful for
me anymore. I'm leaving. I'm just
leaving.
>> You you said that?
>> Yeah. Like I just remember this
happening a couple times and I'm like
wow that was like not like good
behavior.
like I wouldn't like I I I like almost
feel really bad because like the person
running the meeting probably felt really
bad and now I feel like really really
>> Yeah. Yeah. Did HR ever reach out and
say, "Hey, you're you're productive, but
can you be nicer and stuff like that?"
>> Uh, no. I don't I mean I I don't because
I wasn't like mean. It wasn't like a
flip the table type thing. It was like
very and I would talk to the like I had
a good relationship with most like I
think all the PMs I worked with I had a
pretty good relationship with because I
built stuff really fast. I fix bugs
really fast. Like not even my own bugs.
Just like if they h the PMs like the PMs
that a lot of the PMs that I mean Meta
is very high performing company. Almost
everybody's very strong who works there.
And like the PMs are like they want to
like get stuff moving fast. They pay
attention to every pixel and they're
like, "Oh no, this is like broken. This
this test wasn't configured right." And
there's like things that I was very
helpful to PM. So they actually like
liked me a lot. Um, and if I like walked
out of me, if I like had to leave a
meeting, it was like they would almost
like give me permission like, "Yeah,
like Michael, you don't really you're
not needed for this next part of the
meeting, you can go." Like it was not as
jerkish as it sounds. But I just
remember being like that cutthroat where
it was just like like I don't want to
spend times in meetings that I can't be
coding. Like it was like that that uh
that vi that that level of like
strictness. I would say
>> you mentioned that your productivity
over your whole career was was high and
it didn't change that much. It just what
changed was what you wrote code about
and the problems that you solved. How
did you like grow that skill of project
taste or picking problems that mattered
so that the code was more impactful? I I
don't think that so first of all I don't
think that I'm like great great at it
necessarily. I generally picked and I'm
still not good at pri prioritizing in
general. I pick things that I like know
how to do if that makes sense. All
right. I pick things where I see the
answer in my head and um it's just how
fast can I like type or like get this
into the code. Um, and which is also why
LLMs particularly are helping me be
personally so much more efficient
because it's like I have what I want to
do in my head and I need to get it out
fast and LLMs can really help with that.
Yeah. So, sometimes like it might not be
the most impactful thing but it's like a
tricky thing and I have the idea in my
head on how to do it. I might just do it
even though it's not as important as
like another thing. Honestly, this is
probably one of the things that held me
back career-wise. And it was also
frustrating for my managers if they did
try to communicate like, "Hey, this
thing's very important. Can you do
that?" And I'm like, I don't see the
answer to it. Like, it's not I don't I
don't have it. If I don't have it in my
head, I can't do that like super fast. I
like need to have I need to like see the
answer, you know, in a sense. Um, so I'm
going to work on B. It's like, can you
please work on A? It's like I have to do
B C D E F G H. It's like, okay, that's
like a lot of work and that's like
helpful, but like A would be really
good. And I just like I that was like
and I think that that's one of the
things that probably held me back in
general because that limit like if A
really really was so important and I and
it was not done, you know, it's like you
get a passing grade for doing all the
other stuff and it's appreciated, but
like the company would overall impact
would probably be higher by doing a if I
was able to do it. But um I'm somewhat
limited by like what I can figure out
how to do. I frame it as a weakness. But
yeah,
>> that's interesting. So you always
optimize rather than business value
fully. You your rank ordered list of
priorities was what can I just crank out
instantly?
>> Yeah. And if you crank out enough stuff,
it adds up and it can have a huge amount
of impact. But it is definitely
definitely like a a different way of
thinking of work, I think. Yeah. So once
you got promoted to IC7 I think you had
shared that you were added to an IC7
plus only group and I'm curious was
there anything interesting you learned
by being a part of that group or was
there anything common among all the IC7
plus engineers? There's a certain there
was a certain kind of bar that everyone
had regardless of if they were a coding
machine, regardless of if they were a
specialist or a fixer, these different
like
uh reasons why they're there. Um,
everyone had like certain traits that
were common like extremely strong
diligence and conscientiousness.
Um, and very uh I wouldn't say fast or
quick. I don't know the right word, but
like very like sharp. Sharp is the word
I'm looking for. If uh if this group was
even me as someone who I feel like I'm
not I was a very strong student in
school. I was like straight A student. I
think I'm a pretty smart person, but the
most of these people are still are like
smarter. Like these are exceptionally
smart people who I would who I have to
like acknowledge might be smarter than
me. Um, but we all could be in the same
room and talk about something like very
and very quickly move through the
concepts. So like here's this new
proposed protocol and instead of like
having an hourong presentation on it and
discussing it, everyone would be pretty
sharp sharply be like, "Oh, what about
ABCD?" And like the qu follow-up
questions would happen very quickly. Um,
very sharp fast conversations. Um, and
very high attention to detail. Some
people like were really like earlier in
their career accelerated very fast. They
had these traits. Maybe they're
personality traits. Like for me, these
are more personality traits. I would say
like it's like leveraging like OCD and
like a way a productive way to be like
obsessed about every detail of the
product instead of like things that are
not productive. For other people, they
had like their 25 years of experience
and they kind of built these things
through different ways, but like
everyone kind of had that. Um whereas
when a lot of conversations with junior
people there's a lot less cont there's
context missing. There's not necess like
the follow-up questions are not
necessarily as like sharp and on super
fast. It takes a little longer to get
things out. Usually the projects are
smaller in scope as a result and stuff
like that.
>> One thing I want to go over is kind of
like a set of topics on just how do you
how do you land code fast? Like let's
say you're I'm a you know new software
engineer.
I want to absorb your your coding
machine's abilities. Is there a you know
top 20% of tips that get is going to
give me 80% of the benefit to become
more productive? The general advice is
you have to move move you can say it
just in the shortest possible just like
do something like write code. A lot of
people I I who ask me for advice or
questions like they're like thinking too
much about what to do and not doing
enough. Um so like step one is like do
something just do anything. Um and then
step two which is critical is getting
feedback from
uh like respected people or or people
who who have that experience and taste
and judgment or further down the line
and getting feedback from them and then
actioning that um and then repeating. I
thought that my manager hated me because
I was writing so much code so fast that
was like so bad and he was writing he
was doing code reviews and his code
reviews he was like he was like very
frustrated because he was spending like
all day reviewing my code because I was
writing so much code and it had so many
problems and he was just like please
follow the style conventions like there
were please like like these kind of
things right and like it sounds like
that's annoying but that's like step one
is you got to get like the raw the raw
gears turning and then once the gears
are turning getting the feedback and
then iterating. So if you're if you get
feedback like follow the style
guidelines, then you actually have to do
that next time and then there'll be
something else wrong and then you
improve it. And that cycle like that
compounds exceptionally quickly. If
you're writing a lot and you're getting
the getting feedback from experienced
people and you actually action it, it
works really well. The like the biggest
mistakes people make are there's uh
three mistakes I think. The first one
like not turning the gears and not doing
anything like I said earlier. The second
one is not getting feedback from the
right people. So, if you get feedback
from like if you're a boot camp grad and
you're getting feedback from another
boot camp grad who graduated like six
months before you who's like the
instructor now and they're giving you
feedback like as the instructor like
that feedback is probably it doesn't
you're not you you can't it doesn't
encapsulate that experience and taste
and that judgment that you want to learn
from that you're trying to learn from in
this process. it encapsulates the
judgment of someone who's like a little
tiny bit further ahead of you. Um, so
you want to get feedback from people who
have that the judgment and taste that
you aspire to. And then the third
mistake is, and this is a mistake that I
made a lot that I would tell myself to
not do. Um, but is not actioning the
feedback and taking it more like
judgment and approval rather than
feedback. So if someone gives you
feedback and you're taking it as like a
judgment or an approval, you want to
pass the test and it's like you failed
and you want to pass it and you're not
actually reflecting on the feedback.
You're just taking as approval. You're
not going to iterate fast enough. You're
not going to make enough changes. You
might change the wrong things because
you're not accepting the feedback. So if
you do all that, I think you can and and
you do it fast, you can accelerate your
your progress so much. You're saying uh
basically shorten the cycle time and
then make sure you get good feedback and
then internalize it and just that's
going to compound. Just shorten that
loop and just keep going, keep going,
keep going.
>> I see.
>> Let's say I am I'm outputting a ton of
code. I'm already a code machine, but
I'm uh I want to get better. Do you have
any advanced tips on how to take it to
that next level? Let's say I'm pretty
productive already. I would be
ambitious, more ambitious probably if
you're like if you have like your coding
machine thing going like take on
something ambitious that is pushing
yourself a little bit outside of your
normal scope of wherever you're you are
you're in the code or um like this is
very specific to Facebook and Meta
though in general because your impact is
somewhat judged by like breadth and
scope and like
the wider the umbrella, the bigger the
umbrella kind of the more higher level
you are and the more recognition you
get. So like in that environment like if
you're a coding machine on your
department like you got to push beyond
the department and p push your comfort
zone a bit. My advice to my like
something like I saying I'm not good at
accepting prioritization from leaders
but that's actually the advice I would
give though if you're stuck is to ask
like talk like ask your I don't know I
had many many one-on- ones with like the
seauite at Facebook where I was just
like hey Chris Cox like I need I want to
talk to you about this thing and have a
15-minute one-on-one and just if you're
a coding machine that has credibility
already and you're stuck stuck like
reaching out to more senior people in
different areas and trying to get some
ideas of those wider scoped projects if
you're really stuck um can be a step
forward. Coming to the end of the
interview just want to do some you know
career reflections and stuff like that
and you were at Meta for quite a while
and you had a lot of success. I'm
curious why why did you leave Meta and
what was your thinking behind the career
planning there? So Meta got like quite
big quite fast. Um, and there was like
this turning point I six years,
threequarters the way time through there
where I felt like when I was all in on
on Facebook, I felt like it had my back
like 100%. I had their back 100%. It was
like a little bit like culty maybe like
vibes. Um, and then it felt more like a
company, like a business, like a
business relationship. Um, it was
changing. So, that was kind of like the
first sign where I was like open to
leaving. Um, and then I won't go into
all of the details about the vesting
cycles, but there were some vesting
logistics.
Certain years they like had some longer
grants for various reasons and the
vesting cycles and overlapping and
stuff. there was like a very strong
point where it was like your
compensation your take-home pay is going
to drop like 80% in a month like in a
certain over a certain period.
>> So I was kind of like okay you know like
this is maybe the time to like ramp
down. So
>> I think after the previous performance
review cycle when that was coming up I
basically said like I'm going to be
leaving in 3 months. Um, and then I did
a little farewell tour on Messenger for
kids to be like my manager was like,
"Okay, like do you want one last
harrah?" And then they did this project
worked on this project. Um, and I kind
of like slowly ramped down over that
period. Um, and I was like taking home
stuff from my desk every day like slowly
slow ramp down. Um, but it was
definitely it was just kind of that like
at formation now. I mean obviously I'm a
founder so it's also I have more control
over the the that but um it's really
like an all in I'm like allin or not
allin and that allinness like broke like
somewhere threequarters of the time
through through meta as it got bigger
and bigger and I like needed to put that
somewhere else that that dedication
somewhere else.
>> Yeah. I mean getting a 80% pay cut is uh
coupled with the cultural changes you
know makes seems like a good timing to
leave. So when it comes to the highest
levels of performance in IC's, what's
your take on how much of it is talent
and how much of it is hard work and
growth?
>> There is talent. Some people have more
talent than others. Some of it is maybe
your biology. Some of it's just how you
grew up and opportunities you had and
some of it is you have raw talent that's
not discovered yet. there's like all
kinds of views on talent, but it is a
thing and it does come into play. Um, so
there is an aspect of things that are
talent in quotes. If you feel like
you're like, "Oh, no, I'm not talented."
Like you might actually be talented and
it hasn't been discovered yet or you
might be like talented at something that
isn't your day job right now and you
should figure out what that is. And
that's actually like at formation that's
our like big long-term vision is is we
want and why I do what I do every day
now is like we want people doing the
work that is the most impactful work
they can do and we want to help them
find that work because not everyone grew
up the same way with able to explore and
find what that thing is and they might
have not found it yet. We want like, you
know, I feel I feel like everyone has
some kind of talent or something that
they're better than most other people
at. And if you find out what that is,
that is a big piece of the high
performance. And you might not have that
at your day job right now, and it might
limit your performance a little bit.
It's not it's not the whole thing, but
it might limit it. On the other hand, um
hard work is within your control. Um my
friend Philip Zoo talks about this a
lot. Um, but he says like talent is
something outside of your control and
luck is outside of your control, which
is another thing that comes into play
sometimes. But, uh, hard work is the one
thing that's within your control. And if
you maybe aren't you're in a place that
you're you're good at your job, it's
maybe not your like natural talent, but
you're good at it and you like it and
you want to keep your job and you want
to do better, um, you can outwork people
who are similar to you and you will
probably be recognized more
performance-wise as well. What percent
of your career growth would you say is
luck
>> of the growth? Um I think it's 5050 in I
came from Canada. I when I showed up on
my first day of Facebook they gave me I
like grabbed my laptop and left the
onboarding room and they like called me
back because they said that I didn't
have my phone and I didn't know what
they were talking about. It was like
phones like they give you a cell phone
and they gave us like all these
accessories and like this bundle like it
was like they were like red carpet. And
I was like, "What is all this stuff?"
Like, "I just need a computer." Like, it
I came from a place that was a lot more
of like the things you hear about tech
and the way that engineers are like
treated and compensated now is very was
very weird. Um, so if I had like stayed
in Canada and worked at a company, I
would probably be doing quite well, but
like I wouldn't have had the same
acceleration.
Um, the lock was really landing at at
Facebook at the time that I did and it
being like the perfect fit for my
personality at the time and the values
were extremely aligned. Code was like
aligned with what I could handle and
that part is like pure luck. So, I would
maybe just say 50/50. I've seen a lot of
people who don't have the same like
drive and got the luck piece and they're
also doing very well. But like either
one of those could work out and be okay.
But I think I got both of those and that
worked out very well for me personally.
Yeah.
>> Last question. Um if you could speak to
yourself when you just graduated and
give yourself some advice knowing
everything that you know now, what would
you say? I think going back to what I
said earlier, um I was very much and I
see this a lot with people preparing for
interviews at formation nowadays seeking
too much approval for like uh like pats
on the back approval. They want to pass
the test. They want to submit their leak
code and see a green check mark. They
want to um I was that person. I wanted
to get the highest grades and I didn't
really like know what I was learning
even. I just wanted to get like an A+ or
100%. And because of that, I was not
accepting feedback as feedback to
improve. I was accepting feedback as
grade to judge myself and put pressure
on myself to get 100% next time. But I
wasn't putting pressure on myself to
actually improve. So my advice to people
who are ambitious and who want to get
those like perfect scores and check off
all the boxes is to really reflect on
feedback on how you can improve and try
to push your comfort zone there instead
of trying to look at it as a a judgment
or a a grade.
>> Awesome. Well, thanks so much for your
time, Michael. I I was really looking
forward to talking to you and, you know,
hopefully the audience got something
helpful out of this as well.
>> Yeah. And if anyone has any follow-up
questions, I'm like very very
approachable. You can ping me on
LinkedIn or Reddit or whatever and happy
to happy to chat. Hey, thanks for
watching the show. I don't sell anything
or do sponsorships, but if you want to
support, you can subscribe on YouTube or
you can leave a review on Spotify. And
I'm always looking for new guests to
interview. So if anyone comes up who you
think you really want to hear their
career story, uh, let me know and I'll
try to reach out to them and get them on
the show. Thanks for listening as always
and I'll see you next time.